<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>System Administration on Syslogine Docs</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in System Administration on Syslogine Docs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Automating Tasks with Cron</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/automating-tasks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/automating-tasks/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Cron linkBefore diving into the details, let&amp;rsquo;s understand the basic components of cron:&#xA;Crontab: A crontab (cron table) is a file that contains instructions for cron on which commands to run and when to run them. Each user on the system can have their own crontab file.&#xA;Cron Daemon: The cron daemon (crond) is a background process that runs continuously and checks the crontab files at regular intervals to execute the scheduled commands.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Firewall Configuration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/firewall-configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/firewall-configuration/</guid>
      <description>Part 1: Configuring the Firewall with firewalld linkFedora Linux uses firewalld as the default firewall management tool. It provides a user-friendly interface for managing firewall rules and zones.&#xA;1.1 Checking the firewalld Status linkBefore you begin, ensure that firewalld is installed and running. You can check its status with the following command:&#xA;sudo systemctl status firewalld If firewalld is not running, you can start it with:&#xA;sudo systemctl start firewalld 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel Management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/kernel-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/kernel-management/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to the Linux Kernel linkThe Linux kernel is the central component of the Linux operating system. It acts as an interface between the hardware and the user applications, managing system resources and providing various services to the applications. The kernel is responsible for tasks such as process management, memory management, file system management, device management, and network management.&#xA;In Fedora Linux, the kernel is part of the core operating system and is regularly updated to provide bug fixes, security patches, and new features.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Managing System Services</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-services/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Systemd Units linkIn systemd, services are represented as units, which are resources that the system knows how to manage. There are different unit types, but the most common are service units (.service) and socket units (.socket).&#xA;Service Units: Represent system services, such as an HTTP server or a database server. Socket Units: Represent an inter-process communication (IPC) socket, which is used for activating services. Each unit is defined in a unit file, typically located in the /usr/lib/systemd/system/ or /etc/systemd/system/ directories.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Configuration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/network-configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/network-configuration/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Network Configuration linkNetwork configuration in Fedora Linux involves setting up various network components, such as wired or wireless connections, IP addresses, DNS servers, and network interfaces. Fedora provides several tools and utilities to manage network settings, catering to both graphical and command-line preferences.&#xA;Graphical Network Configuration linkGNOME Network Settings linkFedora&amp;rsquo;s default desktop environment, GNOME, includes a graphical network settings tool that allows you to easily configure network connections.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Package Management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/package-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/package-management/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to DNF linkDNF stands for &amp;ldquo;Dandified YUM&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;DNF Next Generation.&amp;rdquo; It is a modern and improved version of the YUM package manager, offering better performance, improved dependency handling, and additional features.&#xA;DNF is a command-line utility that interacts with the package repositories configured on your Fedora system. These repositories contain various software packages, along with their dependencies and metadata.&#xA;Basic DNF Commands linkHere are some of the most commonly used DNF commands:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remote Access and SSH</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/remote-access-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/remote-access-ssh/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Remote Access linkIn this section, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the fundamentals of remote access, its benefits, and common methods used to establish remote connections.&#xA;What is Remote Access? linkRemote access refers to the ability to connect to and interact with a computer or network from a remote location. It enables users to perform tasks, access resources, and manage systems without physically being present at the location of the resources.&#xA;Benefits of Remote Access linkThere are several advantages to remote access, including:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Backup and Restore</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-backup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-backup/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to System Backups linkA system backup is a complete copy of your operating system, applications, configurations, and user data. It serves as a safeguard against data loss, system failures, or accidental deletions. Having a reliable backup strategy in place is essential for any Linux user, whether you&amp;rsquo;re a home user, developer, or system administrator.&#xA;In this tutorial, we will cover various methods for creating system backups on Fedora Linux, including built-in tools like rsync and tar, as well as third-party solutions like Timeshift, Borg Backup, and Duplicity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Logging and Log Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-logging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-logging/</guid>
      <description>Understanding the systemd Journal linkThe systemd journal is a centralized logging system that stores log data in a binary format, making it more efficient and reliable than traditional text-based log files. The journal collects log entries from various components of the system, including the kernel, system services, and user applications. Each log entry contains metadata such as timestamps, source, and priority level, making it easier to filter and analyze log data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Monitoring with systemd</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>Prerequisites linkThis tutorial assumes that you have a Fedora Linux system with systemd installed and configured. Additionally, you should have a basic understanding of the Linux command line and file system.&#xA;Monitoring System Resources linksystemd provides several utilities to monitor system resources, including CPU, memory, and disk usage.&#xA;Monitoring CPU Usage linkTo monitor CPU usage, you can use the systemd-cgtop command, which displays a live view of the CPU usage for all running processes and services.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Performance Tuning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-performance/</guid>
      <description>Introduction linkSystem performance tuning is the process of adjusting various system components and configurations to optimize the overall performance of your computer. This process can involve tweaking settings related to disk usage, memory management, CPU usage, and networking, among others.&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s important to note that performance tuning is a complex topic, and the techniques discussed in this tutorial may not be suitable for all systems or use cases. It&amp;rsquo;s recommended to thoroughly understand the implications of each change and to perform thorough testing before implementing any changes in a production environment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Security Best Practices</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-security/</guid>
      <description>1. User Authentication link1.1 Strong Password Policies linkImplement strong password policies to prevent brute-force attacks and unauthorized access. Here are some recommendations:&#xA;Set a minimum password length (e.g., 12 characters) Require a combination of uppercase, lowercase, numbers, and special characters Enable password aging and expiration policies Disable password reuse To configure password policies, edit the /etc/security/pwquality.conf file and modify the relevant settings.&#xA;1.2 Restrict Root Access linkAvoid using the root account for daily tasks, as it grants unrestricted access to the system.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Updates and Patch Management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/system-updates/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Software Updates linkSoftware updates are released for various reasons, including:&#xA;Security Patches: These updates address known security vulnerabilities and are critical for protecting your system against potential threats. Bug Fixes: Updates often include fixes for identified software bugs, improving stability and performance. Feature Enhancements: New features and improvements are introduced through software updates. Regularly applying updates ensures that your system remains secure, stable, and up-to-date with the latest features and improvements.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User Management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/user-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/user-management/</guid>
      <description>Creating a New User Account linkTo create a new user account in Fedora, use the useradd command. The basic syntax is:&#xA;sudo useradd [options] username Here are some common options:&#xA;-c &amp;quot;Comment&amp;quot;: Adds a comment or description for the user. -d /home/directory: Specifies the user&amp;rsquo;s home directory (default is /home/username). -g group: Sets the primary group for the user. -G groups: Adds the user to supplementary groups. -s shell: Specifies the user&amp;rsquo;s login shell (default is /bin/bash).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtualization with KVM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/virtualization-kvm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/os/fedora/administration/virtualization-kvm/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to KVM linkKVM is a kernel module that provides hardware-assisted virtualization support on x86 hardware with virtualization extensions (Intel VT or AMD-V). It transforms the Linux kernel into a hypervisor, allowing it to run multiple virtual machines securely and efficiently.&#xA;KVM has several advantages over other virtualization solutions:&#xA;Performance: KVM provides near-native performance for virtual machines due to hardware-assisted virtualization. Open-source: KVM is an open-source solution and part of the Linux kernel, making it free and accessible.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
